

(+1) 847-641-0586 <u>kaiyuhou2022@u.northwestern.edu</u> <u>www.kyhou.com</u> 1111 Church St. Apt. 605 Evanston, IL, 60201

I am currently a fourth year Ph.D. candidate in the Computer Science Department at Northwestern University, advised by Prof. Yan Chen. I have a broad interest in various aspects of cloud networks and network protocols. My current research focuses on network optimization of microservices/serverless based cloud. I am also working for introducing formal methods into network protocol verification.

Education

• Ph.D. Student in Computer Science Northwestern University

2017 - (2022)

Evanston, IL

- Advisor: Prof. Yan Chen

- Area: Networked System, Cloud Networking

- GPA: 3.97/4.0

 Master's in Computer Science Xi'an Jiaotong University 2014 - 2017

Shaanxi, China

- Advisor: Prof. Chengchen Hu

- Area: Software Defined Networking (SDN)

- Rank: 1st/89 GPA: 3.81/4.0 Average: 91.7

• B.E. in Software Engineering Xi'an Jiaotong University

2010 - 2014

Shaanxi, China

- Rank: 1st/78 GPA: 3.94/4.0 Average: 92.4 (in Junior and Senior year)

Work Experiences

• SRI International

Menlo Park, CA

Research Intern, at Computer Science Laboratory

Jun. 2020 - Sep. 2020

- Advisor: Dr. Vinod Yegneswaran
- Designed and implemented an enterprise-wide radio situational awareness system
- Passively collected radio traffics, including Wi-Fi and Bluetooth, analyzed by deep learning

Research: Cloud Networks & SDN

• Network Optimizing for Microservices/Serverless Cloud (work in progress)

2020 - Present

- Microservice/serverless architecture brings flexibility but introduces network communication delay
- Aim to design systematic metrics to provide a benchmark for the microservice network performance
- Integrated QUIC into **OpenFaaS/Kubernetes** to improve serverless network performance

• Generic Security Policy Enforcement System for SDN-based Cloud

2017 - 2018

- Designed a **policy language** for resource protection and management of SDN-based Cloud
- Implemented in the **OpenDaylight** controller, and deployed on **OpenStack**

Publication: [IWQoS'18] Lightweight Resource Protection and Management System for SDN-based Cloud

- Routing Policy for Solving Reactive Model Overhead of Software Defined Networks 2016 2017
 - Proposed a routing policy to reduce the control channel bandwidth consumption up to 80%
 - Implemented in the **Floodlight** controller under the **OpenFlow** protocol with **Open vSwitch**
 - Deployed on the ONetSwitch, an OpenFlow white-box switch with Xilinx FPGA

Publication: [ICNP'17] SoftRing: Taming the reactive model for software defined networks

Research: Formal Methods for Network Protocols

• Formal Verification and Vulnerability Detection of LTE/5G Protocols

2019 - 2020

- Used **TLA+** to formally specify the emergency call systems in **4G/5G** cellular network protocols
- Built a complete cellular network testbed (USRP, OpenAirInterface) and verified these issues
- Discovered serious availability and security issues in real-world, acknowledged by major carriers

Publication: [Under Review] Discovering Emergency Call Pitfalls for Cellular Networks with Formal Methods

- Formal Secure Configuration Search for Network Protocols (work in progress) 2020 Present
 - Traditionally, researchers use secure properties to verify a protocol is safe or find counterexamples
 - We convert this decision problem into a search problem. Given the model and the properties, we aim to search the boundaries of the configuration space where the system is always secure and reliable.
 - We employ inductive generalization and improved IC3 algorithm to determine the space.

Publication: [Sigcomm'20 Poster] Network Protocol Safe Configuration Search in One Shot

Publication List

- Discovering Emergency Call Pitfalls for Cellular Networks with Formal Methods
 Kaiyu Hou*, You Li*, Yinbo Yu, Yan Chen, Hai Zhou (*equal contribution)
 Under Review
- Network Protocol Safe Configuration Search in One Shot
 You Li*, Kaiyu Hou*, Hai Zhou, Yan Chen (*equal contribution)
 ACM Special Interest Group on Data Communication (SIGCOMM, Poster), 2020.
- State of the Art and Research Challenges in the Security Technologies of Network Function Virtualization
 Xiaochun Wu, Kaiyu Hou, Xue Leng, Xing Li, Yinbo Yu, Bo Wu, Yan Chen
 IEEE Internet Computing, 2020
- CellScope: Automatically Specifying and Verifying Cellular Network Protocols
 Yinbo Yu, You Li, Kaiyu Hou, Yan Chen, Hai Zhou, Jianfeng Yang

 ACM Special Interest Group on Data Communication (SIGCOMM, Poster), 2019

- A Lightweight Policy Enforcement System for Resource Protection and Management in the SDN-based Cloud Xue Leng, Kaiyu Hou, Yan Chen, Kai Bu, Libin Song, You Li Computer Networks, Elsevier, 2019
- *COIN: A fast packet inspection method over compressed traffic*Xiuwen Sun, Hao Li, Dan Zhao, Xingxing Lu, **Kaiyu Hou**, Chengchen Hu
 Journal of Network and Computer Applications, Elsevier, 2019
- SDNKeeper: Lightweight Recource Protection and Management System for SDN-based Cloud Xue Leng, Kaiyu Hou, Yan Chen, Kai Bu, Libin Song IEEE/ACM 26th International Symposium on Quality of Service (IWQoS), 2018
- SoftRing: Taming the reactive model for software defined networks
 Chengchen Hu, Kaiyu Hou (1st student author), Hao Li, Ruilong Wang, Peng Zheng, Peng Zhang,
 Huanzhao Wang
 IEEE 25th International Conference on Network Protocols (ICNP), 2017
- Towards A Fast Packet Inspection over Compressed HTTP Traffic
 Xiuwen Sun, Kaiyu Hou, Hao Li, Chengchen Hu
 IEEE/ACM 25th International Symposium on Quality of Service (IWQoS), 2017

Teaching Experiences

•	CS 214: Data Structure and Data Management Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University	Winter, 2021
•	CS 214: Data Structure and Data Management Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University	Fall, 2020
•	CS 212, Mathematical Foundations of Computer Science Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University	Spring, 2020
•	CS 340, Introduction to Networking (Best Teaching Assistant Award) Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University	Winter, 2020
•	CS 214, Data Structure and Data Management Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University	Fall, 2019
•	EECS 343, Operating Systems Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University	Spring, 2019
•	EECS 340, Introduction to Networking Assistant Lecturer, Northwestern University	Winter, 2019
•	EECS 340, Introduction to Networking Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University	Fall, 2018
•	IT 458, Information Security and Assurance Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University	Winter, 2018

• Computer Programming (C++) for CS Honored Class Teaching Assistant, Xi'an Jiaotong University

Fall, 2016

Professional Services

- Sub-reviewer of ACM CCS (2018, 2019)
- Sub-reviewer of IEEE ICDCS (2018)
- Reviewer of IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking (ToN)

Awards

Tivarab	
Bronze Medal, ACM-ICPC Asia Regional Contest	2012, 2013, 2014
Silver Medal, ACM-ICPC China Province Contest, Chengdu	2012, 2013
• Meritorious Winner, Mathematical Contest in Modeling (MCM)	2013
Honor	
• Best Teaching Assistant Award (<i>Peter and Adrienne Barris</i> Outstanding TA) <i>Northwestern University</i>	2020
• Graduate (Cadre) with Honor Xi'an Jiaotong University	2017
• Excellent Postgraduate Student Leader Award Xi'an Jiaotong University	2015, 2016
• Graduate with Honor Xi'an Jiaotong University	2014
• Excellent Student Model Nomination (16/13000) Xi'an Jiaotong University	2013
• Google Excellence Scholarship Awarded to 3 students from each of 20 top Chinese universities	2013
• Excellent Student Award Xi'an Jiaotong University	2011, 2012, 2013
Social Activities	
• Student President of Computer Science Dept., (Class 2017) <i>Xi'an Jiaotong University</i>	2014 - 2017
• Student Councilor , the Student Congress of ChungYing College <i>Xi'an Jiaotong University</i>	2013 - 2014
• Chair, the ACM-ICPC Club Xi'an Jiaotong University	2012 - 2013

•	Science and Education Minister of Student Union	2011-2012
	Xi'an Jiaotong University	
•	Co-Founder & the 2 nd Store Manager of Bingo Cafe	2010-2013
	ChungYing College, Xi'an Jiaotong University	

Skills

- L2/L3/L4 Protocols, 3GPP Cellular Network Protocols (NAS layer), 802.11 Protocols, QUIC Protocols
- Serverless Platforms, Microservice Networks, Cloud Networks, SDN
- Formal Methods for Network Protocols
- Python, Go-lang